Guide to the Papers of Simon Dubnow (1860-1941) 1589-1938, 1961 (bulk 1700-1900) RG 87
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
- Series I: Pinkasim (communal registers), 1589-1900; 19 folders
  - Pitrovits (Piotrowice)[I.2], 1726-1809 (Folder 917, Item 73152-73213)
    the older pagination continues to pp. 68, the newer pagination, in pencil to pp. 92
    missing: pp. 28, 31, 33, 36, 55
    the outer half of pp. 76 is torn away
  - Bikhov (Bychow)[I.3], 1686-1869 (Folder 918, Item 73214-73258)
    register of the hevra kadisha (burial society), copied from the original pinkas in 1869 by Yirmiyah, son of Avraham Yermanakh, Hebrew, copy, 45 pp., bound
  - Tiktin (Tykocin)[I.4], 1589-1816 (Folder 919, Item 73259-73316)
    communal register of Tiktin and its environs, partial copy
    the original pinkas that Dubnow received in 1895 from Dr. Yosef Chazanovitsh of Bialystok contains 489 pp. in folio of which pp. 1-23 were missing
    Hebrew, Yiddish
  - Zabludow[I.5], 1650-1827 (Folder 920, Item 73317-73338)
    communal register, copy, 20 pp., Hebrew and Yiddish
  - Birzai (Birzh, Birze)[I.6, I.7], 1784-1836 (Folder 921, Item 73339-73386)
    two registers of the hevra kadisha, partial copy, including by-laws of the burial society and some records of the years 5544-5596
  - Pinczow[I.8], 1632-1740 (Folder 922, Item 73387-73395)
    a few pages of sample notations from the pinkas, 8 pp., Hebrew, edges damaged
  - Lublin[I.9], 1685-1695, 1777-1785 (Folder 923, Item 73396-73444)
    communal register, partial copy
    the original is 92 pp. long, Hebrew and Yiddish
    copies of documents, 1685-1695, 1777-1785
    the introduction and a few documents reprinted in Nisnboym, Le-korot ha-yehudim be-Lublin (Chronicles of the Jews in Lublin), published in Lublin in 5660 (1900)
  - Pinkas medinat Lita, 1895 (Folder 924, Item 73445)
    excerpts, supplement to a letter from Sh. Beilin of Luck to Dubnow, September 1
  - Pinkas medinat Lita[I.10], 1894 (Folder 925, Item 73446-73526)
    partial copy, a collection of statutes of the Councils of Lithuania, 1664-1761, copied in the Strashun Library in Vilna in 1894
  - Pinkas medinat Lita, 1883-1895 (Folder 926, Item 73527-73554)
    supplements to folder 925, marked A to D
    Reel 74
  - Horodno[I.11], 1882 (Folder 927, Item 73555-73632)
    content index referring to statutes #1-941, 20 pp.
    copy of statutes #954, and others
    proofsheets of the Pinkas Horodno, not complete
  - Pinkas medinat Lita[I.12], 1886 (Folder 928, Item 73633-73715)
    register of the Council of Lithuania, partial copy by A.L. Faynshtayn in 1886 from the Brest copy of the Pinkas medinat Lita, Hebrew, 79 pp.
  - Dubno[I.13], 1670-1671 (Folder 929, Item 73716-73721)
    excerpts from the pinkas, Council of the Four Lands
    documents regarding Lublin (1670) and Jaroslaw (1671), copied from the original in Jewish Historical Ethnographic Society in St. Petersburg, Hebrew, 6 pp.
  - Libau, Courland[I.14], 1850 (Folder 930, Item 73722-73725)
    pinkas of the burial society, 4 pp.
  - Kedainiai (Keydan)[I.16b], 1702 (Folder 930, Item 73726 A and B)
    wax seal from the pinkas of “Mitsvah Activists” Society, 5462
  - Mstislavl[I.15a], 1702-1823 (Folder 931, Item 73726)
    pinkas of Mstislavl and environs, a note
    I.15a-I.17 are on the same two sheets of paper
  - Kedainiai (Keydan) (Folder 932, Item 73727)
    pinkas, a note
  - Liozni (Liozna)[I.18], 1750-1820 (Folder 933, Item 73727-73733)
    pinkas of the hevra kadisha, partial copy, deals with Hasidim
- Series II: Civilia, 1638-1909; 11 folders
  This series consists of documents about the legal status and the political situation of Jews in Russia and Poland, mainly in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Included are privileges and deeds granted to Jews by various rulers in Eastern Europe, official documents regarding the policies of tsars Nicholas I and Alexander II, documents concerning Max Lilienthal’s efforts to establish state schools for Jewish children in Russia, and materials about the Karaites. This series includes several samples of martyrological literature, such as prayers and lamentations in memory of the victims of pogroms in the times of Bogdan Chmielnicki (1648) and Ivan Gonta (1768).
  - Listing of documents in the Civilia section, undated (Folder 934, Item 7734-73736)
  - Pinkas of the Council of Four Lands of the Kingdom of Poland: Addendum[II.1], 1892 (Folder 935, Item 73737)
    excerpt from the book “Ma'amar kadishin”, 1764, about the laws regarding one who flees from his creditors, copied by Shim'on Goldlast, Lomza, 1 pp.
  - Rabbi Meyer Hirshl Margolius[II.2], 1892 (Folder 935, Item 73738-73739)
    royal decree by King Stanislaw August, appointing the rabbi of Ostroh, R’ Meyer Hirshl Margolius, the rabbi of Bratslav and the Ukraine, January 1775, Polish
    copied from the original by his grandson, Avraham Rabinovitsh in Mohilev Podolsk, with an addendum about R’ Meyer Margolius written by Menahem Nahum Litinsky, Mohilev Podolsk, 13 Elul 5652
  - Contract between the kehilla of Ostroh and R' Meyer Margolius[II.3], 1777-1778 (Folder 935, Item 73740)
    contract appointing him rabbi and chief of beit din of Ostroh and its environs, 1777 (renewed in 1778), 1 pp., copied by Menahem Nahum Litinsky
  - Contract between the kehilla of Ostroh and R' Meyer Margolius[II.4], undated (Folder 935, Item 73741-73742)
    copy of the above
  - Edict of Herzog Ferdinand about the banishment of Jews from Courland[II.5], 1839 (Folder 935, Item 73743-73744)
    banishment as of 23 March, 1714
    copy of printed version in “Inland”, #48, 3 pp., German
  - Decree by Herzog Karl[II.6], 1760 (Folder 935, Item 73745-73746)
    decree of September 20, 1760 about the expulsion of Jews from Courland
    compare II.5 and the letters from Goetz to Dubnow
  - Letters from the mortgage holders in the Podlasie Province[II.7], 1825 (Folder 935, Item 73747-73749)
    to the council members of the Committee for Jewish Affairs in Warsaw, 9 Heshvan 5585, about their difficult condition
  - Letter from Zalman Posner to the community elders (parnasim) of Suwalki[II.8], 1843 (Folder 935, Item 73750-73751)
    elders are Yehezkel Lipsky, Avraham Rosenthal, Moshe Epshteyn, from Warsaw
    about projects regarding the status of the peasantry
    history of the Jews of Sniadow, written by Pinhas Turberg, Jedwabne, Lomza Province, 4 pp.
  - Excerpts from Responsa, Ateret-Tzvi[II.9], 1720-1721 (Folder 935, Item 73752-73753)
    pp. 183, notation #25, regarding Rabbi Tzvi son of Azriel of Vilna and his trial, 5480-5481, 4 pp.
  - Jews and the jurisdiction of the Polish courts[II.10], 1792 (Folder 936, Item 73754-73757)
    Vilna, original, dated 5 May, 4 pp., Polish
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], 1841-1846 (Folder 936, Item 73758-73795)
    five official documents, Russian, 35 pp.
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], 1841 (Folder 936, Item 73758-73765)
    a) letter from Count Kiselev to the governor-general of Novorussia with an addendum about the need for reforming Jewish life in Russia, 13 February, Russian, 8 pp., copy
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], 1841 (Folder 936, Item 73766-73773)
    b) memorandum from the Chief of the Interior Ministry, F. Stroganov, to the governor-general of Novorussia and Bessarabia about the proposed reforms regarding the Jews, 19 February, Russian, copy, 8 pp.
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], 1844 (Folder 936, Item 73774-73781)
    c) decree by the emperor Nicholas I, regarding ways to educate Jews in Russia, copy, 5 pp.
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], undated (Folder 936, Item 73782-73793)
    d) regulations about Jewish schools and teachers under supervision of the Ministry for Public Education, copy, 12 pp.
  - Committee for the History of Odessa Jews[II.11], 1844 (Folder 936, Item 73794-73795)
    e) letter from Minister Perovsky to Count (Baron) Vorontsoff, about the laws pertaining to Jewish residence in cities, 3 August, Russian, copy, 2 pp.
  - Adolf Lasky[II.12], 1835 (Folder 937, Item 73796-73797)
    a) certificate for Adolf Lasky about his completing the 3rd grade at the Odessa Jewish school, 10 September, original, Russian, 2 pp., seal
  - Adolf Lasky[II.12], 1836 (Folder 937, Item 73798-73799)
    b) graduation certificate for Adolf Lasky from the Odessa Jewish school, 20 August, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Adolf Lasky[II.12], 1897 (Folder 937, Item 73800-73801)
    c) letter from Adolf Lasky to Dubnow, dated January 10, about the above two certificates, Russian, 2 pp.
  - 1000-year celebration of Russian empire[II.13], 1862-1863 (Folder 937, Item 73802-73803)
    a) letter from Ya'akov Barit (Kovner) to Yehoshua Heshel Levin in Vilna, Monday, 12 Tishrei 5623, about the Jewish delegation from Vilna to St. Petersburg for the 1000-year celebration of Russian empire in September 1862
    excerpts from the book “Pleitat sofrim,” by Yehoshua Heshel of Vilna, 1863, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - 1000-year celebration of Russian empire[II.13], 1862 (Folder 937, Item 73804)
    b) address from Vilna kehilla to Tsar Alexander II, in honor of the 1000-year celebration of Russia, 8 September, Hebrew translation from Russian by Ya'akov Barit (Kovner)
  - Karaites[II.14], 1887 (Folder 937, Item 73805-73806)
    a) About Karaites, by Shimen Stanislavsky, Yekaterinoslav, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Karaites[II.14], 1888 (Folder 937, Item 73807)
    b) S. Y. Stanislavsky’s article about the Karaites, “Chronicle of the Karaite Literature”, Hamelitz, no. 243, November 28
  - Karaites[II.14], 1896 (Folder 937, Item 73808-73809)
    c) copy from Polin-Chronicles regarding the influx of Karaites into Lithuania, Volhynia and Galicia according to a Karaite manuscript of 5555 (1795)
    copied by Shmuel Berav Moyshe and affirmed by Yitzhak Altansky, Bakhtshisaray, 11 January, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Karaites[II.14], 1896 (Folder 937, Item 73810)
    d) mailing envelope from Altansky from Bakhtshisaray, addressed to the head of the Karaite Synagogue in Odessa, Yehudah Berav Yitzhak Savaliskan, 11 January, Russian
  - Karaites[II.14], 1892 (Folder 937, Item 73811-73812)
    e) article by M. N. Litinsky of Mohilev-Podolsk, about the Karaites with notes by Elishah Lenovits, July 10
    letter to Avraham Firkovitch about the Karaites, copied from a 1865 manuscript in possession by Kordo of Krasna, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1785 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    a) Shabtai Katz, introduction to Penitential Prayers and Lamentations for the Evil Events in Ukraine, Volhynia and Podolya, and in Lithuania in the years 1648-1649, copy from a selihot, printed in Amsterdam by Yohanan Levi Rofe, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1892 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    b) same as above, copied and with comment by Shalom Aleksander Rivkin of Homel, Mohilev Province, 23 December, Hebrew, 8 pp.
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1658 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    c) selihot, composed by R' Yehiel Mikhel of Nemirov, following the events of Takh-ve-Tat (1648-1649)
    copied from the book Kol Ya'akov (The Voice of Jacob), Venice, 5418, Hebrew, 2 pp., folio
    Yalkut Hiyug (Hayim Yonah Gurland) of Kuntres, pp. 32, note 29
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1794 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    d) selihot, copied by Eliezer Yitzhak Feygin, Bialystok, from Seder ha-Selihot (Book of Mourning/Penitential prayers), printed in Poritsk, Hebrew, 2 pp., folio
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1708 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    e) selihot, written in Kol Ya'akov by Ya'akov Kopl, son of Tzvi Margolies, Amsterdam, 5468
  - Khmelnitsky pogroms of 1648-1649 (Takh-ve-Tat)[II.15], 1893 (Folder 938, Item 73813-73828)
    f) R’ Ya'akov Emden’s reports about the horrors of Takh-ve-Tat, derived from his autobiographic text, Megillat sefer, by Hayim Eliezer Dubnikov of Tulczyn, 11 June
    supplement from Tiferet Yisrael by Yisroel Zuta about the 1648-1649 catastrophe, Hebrew, 8 pp.
  - Penitentials and lamentations[II.16], 1638 (Folder 939, Item 73829-73833)
    selihot ve-kinot about the martyrs Moshe and Yehudah, murdered in Warsaw in 5396
  - Folksongs about persecutions[II.17], 1768 (Folder 939, Item 73834-73839)
    Gezerot Takh-ve-Tat and Gezerot Gonte (Gonta), 5528
  - Folksongs about persecutions[II.17], undated (Folder 939, Item 73834-73839)
    a) folksongs about the persecutions in Podolia
    Memorial Chronicles of Jews in Podolia in the days of the Cossack Uprising
    sent by Menahem Nahum Litinsky
    detailed reproduction with citations from the Russian and Yiddish folksongs about the factual historic events of the atrocities, with a Hebrew translation, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Folksongs about persecutions[II.17], 1893 (Folder 939, Item 73834-73839)
    b) From the History of Jews in Podolya, a rare document regarding Gezerot Gonte, by Menahem Nahum Litinsky, Mohilev Podolsk, 22 June 1890
    printed in Russian translation by Dubnow in Voskhod in 1893, as Platsh ukrainskogo evreia
  - Catastrophes[II.18], 1890-1893 (Folder 939, Item 73840-73843)
    a) Sha'ar ha-melekh by R’ Mordekhai, chief of the beit din of Vilkotch, printed Horodno 1790
    copy from the book, by Pinhas Ha-kohen Turberg, 7 Elul 5652, Jedwabne
    about the atrocities of 5528 (1768) in Uman and other places, 4 pp., Hebrew
    with Dubnow’s reference to Hayim Yonah Gurland’s Chronicles of the Horrors, Odessa, 5653, 81 pp.
  - Catastrophes[II.18], 1791 (Folder 939, Item 73840-73843)
    b) blood libel in the City of Turzysk, Volhynia and Kovel, 5551
    two stories about the cases in Turzysk and in Kovel, Yiddish, 4 pp.
  - Letters from Yitzhak Nisnboym[II.19], 1894 (Folder 940, Item 73844-73846)
    a) Rosh Hodesh Tevet 5655
  - Letters from Yitzhak Nisnboym[II.19], 1894 (Folder 940, Item 73844-73846)
    b) 10 Av 5655, with excerpt from various books:
    Beit lehem Yehudah
    She'elot u-teshuvot heishiv Eliezer: responsa by Mordekhai Ziskind Rutenberg
    teshuvot of the great scholars
    Emunat Yisrael
    other excerpts, about the massacres and persecutions in Moscow, Bychow, Mohilev, Pereyaslav, and others, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - Persecutions of Jews[II.20], 1895 (Folder 940, Item 73847-73849)
    excerpts from various books, such as Rosh Yosef, Even ha-shoham, Kikayon de-Yonah
    copied by Shapiro, Mezrich, 22 Av, 5655, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - El mole rakhamim[II.21], 1895 (Folder 940, Item 73850-73853)
    for the victims of Takh-ve-Tat (1648-1649); and of the Gonta rebellion (1743) in Pavlitsh, Tvarov, Mohilev, Nesvizh, and Chernigov
    memorial prayer for the many righteous victims, reproduced from an old pinkas of Nesvizh by Shmuel David Faynberg’s son, with a comment by Shmuel David Faynberg, dated 7 Shevat, 5655, 4 pp., Hebrew
  - Sales, merchandising matters, taxes, rentals, and mortgages[II.22], 1896 (Folder 940, Item 73854-73855)
    statutes from R’ Feibush of Krakow, the Ba'al ha-Taz of Lvov and others
    copies of these laws, as per the manuscript by Isser Nastashkin in Belotserkov, 3 Tevet 5656, with comments, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - Note from the Vilna Police[II.23], 1908 (Folder 940, Item 73856)
    refers to prohibition of Jews to live on the most prominent streets of Vilna, 10 September, 1823, Yiddish and Polish, 1 pp.
    remarks in Dubnow’s hand, in Russian
  - Writ of Orders from the governor of Grodno[II.24], 1852 (Folder 940, Item 73857-73859)
    Ukase from the Governor about Hair of Females
    refers to prohibition of shaving Jewish women’s scalp, Russian, 3 pp.
  - Address to Nicholas II, from the Society of True Russian Men in Odessa[II.25], 1909 (Folder 941, Item 73860-73861)
    on the occasion of Nicholas II's passage through Odessa in September, Russian, 2 pp.
    draft, signatures were collected but the writ was never handed over
  - Dr. Lilienthal[II.26], 1842-1844 (Folder 942, Item 73862-73870)
    thank you letter for Dr. Lilienthal in regard to his mission on behalf of the Ministry of Public Education, signed by Minister Perovsky, St. Petersburg, 29 July 1842
    copy, 1 pp. Russian
    two more letters attesting to the importance of Lilienthal’s mission, June 22, 1842
    letters to Lilienthal, Yiddish, German, St. Petersburg, 10 July 1842
    Ukase by the Tsar to the Minister of Public Education, 13 November, 1844
  - Committee for Jewish Affairs in Warsaw[II.27], 1846 (Folder 943, Item 73871-73874)
    documents regarding an imperial order of February 18, regarding restrictions on Jewish residence
    instructions on how to “enlighten” the Jewish masses about these restrictions, January 26
  - Committee for Jewish Affairs in Warsaw[II.28], 1825 (Folder 943, Item 73875-73880)
    request of the renters of Podlasie Province, dated 8 Heshvan, 5586, about their stressful situation
    compare to II.7 above
  - (Missing) Letter about farm laborers[II.29], 1844 (Folder 943)
    Zalmen Posner to the councilors /parnasim of Suwalki, copy, 1844 (1843?), Hebrew, 2 pp.
    compare to II.8 above
  - Circular about Zionist enclaves[II.30], 1903 (Folder 944, Item 73881)
    circular by Plehve and Lopukhin about supervision and steps to be taken to obstruct Jewish national movements, 24 June
  - Call from the Odessa Union of the Russian People to the Jews[II.31], 1909 (Folder 944, Item 73882)
    concerning the elections to national Duma of 28 September
    signed by B. A. Pelikan, printed flyer, 1 pp., Russian
- Series III: Communalia, 1660-1912; 13 folders
  This series is centered on local history, documenting approximately thirty-five communities in Ukraine, Belarus and Poland. Materials are organized by community name. This diverse series contains excerpts from pinkasim, materials about blood libels and other proceedings against Jews, including those in Mezrich, the Velizh trial, 1823-1835 and in Novy Ushitsa, 1838-1840, martyrological texts, and tombstone inscriptions.
  - Statutes from the pinkas of the Hevra Kadisha Baranovka[III.1], 1780 (Folder 945, Item 73883-73885)
    excerpts from old books about victims of persecutions, Hebrew, 6 pp.
  - Ukase about punishing the convert Grudinsky for libeling Jews[III.2], 1830 (Folder 945, Item 73886-73887)
    in connection with the Velizh court case, 10 July, Russian, 3 pp.
  - Privilege given to the Jews of Bychow[III.3], 1880 (Folder 945, Item 73888-73889)
    privilege given by the Lithuanian vice-chancellor, Michal Sapieha, 17 February 1758
    confirmed in 1827 and 1880, Polish, copy, 1 pp.
  - Statutes of the Hevra Kadisha Gomlei Hasadim of Belotserkov[III.4], 1772 (Folder 945, Item 73890)
    for the year 5532, copy, Hebrew, 1 pp.
  - Documents about Bialystok[III.5], undated (Folder 945, Item 73891-73897)
    a) list of inscriptions on gravestones from the Bialystok cemetery for the years 5570-5620 (1810-1860), with remarks by Dr. Yosef Chazanovitsh, Bialystok, Hebrew, 5 pp.
  - Documents about Bialystok[III.5], 1789 (Folder 945, Item 73891-73897)
    b) rabbinic certification for Shlomo Zalman Tiktin in Bialystok, dated 5549, copy, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Documents regarding the Velizh trial, 1823-1835[III.6], 1893 (Folder 945, Item 73898-73925)
    a) excerpts from the Senate proceeding compiled by Dubnow in the form of a notebook titled Zapiski Velizhe, June, 82 pp., Russian
  - Documents regarding the Velizh trial, 1823-1835[III.6], 1893 (Folder 945, Item 73898-73925)
    b) three letters to Dubnow about the Velizh blood libel, by L. N. Etinger, Velizh, 19 April, 26 May and 29 June, Russian, 16 pp.
  - Documents regarding the Velizh trial, 1823-1835[III.6], 1893-1894 (Folder 945, Item 73898-73925)
    c) two letters to Dubnow about the Velizh Trial from Hayim Rivkin, Velizh, 21 November and 9 January, Russian, 16 pp.
  - Documents regarding the Velizh trial, 1823-1835[III.6], undated (Folder 945, Item 73898-73925)
    d) Dubnow’s remarks and bibliographic notes appended to the Velizh proceedings, Russian, 10 pp.
  - History of Jews in Vizhun and Utian (Russia)[III.7], 1894 (Folder 946, Item 73926-73941)
    a) Chronicles of the City in Vizhun, a letter to Dubnow from Nahum-Ber Garb, dated 4 February, Vilkomir, with excerpts from the statutes of the Hevra Tehillim in Utian (Kovno Gubernia), Hebrew, 8 pp.
  - History of Jews in Vizhun and Utian (Russia)[III.7], 1893-1894 (Folder 946, Item 73926-73941)
    b) materials about the martyr, R’ Menahem Man of Vizhun
  - History of Jews in Vizhun and Utian (Russia)[III.7], 1912 (Folder 946, Item 73926-73941)
    c) letter from Azriel Yafat and Ben-Tzion Tsun Yehaya and materials about R’ Menakhem Man, 7 February, Russian and Hebrew, 10 pp.
  - Gravestone from the old cemetery in Homel[III.8], 1898 (Folder 947, Item 73942)
    from the year 5512 (1752), in the courtyard of Babushkins' Shul, copy by Dubnow, 24 August 1898, 1 pp., Hebrew
    remarks by Dubnow, Russian
  - Excerpts from the Dubno pinkasim[III.9], 1892-1893 (Folder 947, Item 73943-73946)
    excerpts from 17th and 18th century, printed in Hamelitz, 1892, # 124, 233, 241, and 1893, #63 by Khayim Margolis
    sent to Dubnow with a Russian addendum by Shalom Rabinovitch (Sholem Aleichem)
  - Inscriptions from Kishinev cemetery[III.10], 1894 (Folder 947, Item 73947)
    inscriptions from 1712-1794, by Ze'ev Volf Vaynshteyn, in a letter to Dubnow, 18 October
    [III.11 not used]
  - Privilege for Jews in Kritchev, Mohilev Province[III.12], 1893 (Folder 947, Item 73948)
    privilege issued by the King Jan Kazimierz, 1664
    translation done by a Russian notary on 12 October, 1893
  - Letters about the Jewish Community of Liozna[III.13], 1898-1899 (Folder 947, Item 73949-73954)
    three letters from Dr. Avraham Bramson, of Liozna, Mohilev Province, 8 December, 22 January and 7 June, Russian, 5 pp.
  - Letter with an inscription on the gravestone of the martyr Ze'ev Volf[III.14], 1892 (Folder 947, Item 73955-73956)
    killed in 1762 in Lutsk
    from L. Binshtok, 6 December
  - History of the Jews in Lublin[III.15], 1894 (Folder 948, Item 73957-73969)
    a) listing of 26 gravestones, in the Lublin cemetery, sent to Dubnow by R' Yosef Levinshteyn, rabbi of Serock, Adar 5654, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - History of the Jews in Lublin[III.15], 1895 (Folder 948, Item 73957-73969)
    b) massacre of 5417 (1657) from old responsa
    the fire of 5367 (1607)
    in a letter by Ya'akov Shapiro, Mezrich, Tishrei 5656, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - History of the Jews in Lublin[III.15], 1892 (Folder 948, Item 73957-73969)
    c) letter from Tuva Habavli, Kovno, 16 December, with passages from responsa Yosef da'at (Mounting Knowledge), about Lublin, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - History of the Jews in Lublin[III.15], 1895 (Folder 948, Item 73957-73969)
    d) letter and card from Shlomo Nisnboym of Lublin, 12 February and 3 March
    with inscription on the 5396 (1646) gravestone of the martyr R' Nahman
  - Mezrich (Miedzyrzec)[III.16], undated (Folder 949, Item 73970-73989)
    a) income and expense ledger for the Kehilla of Mezrich, covering the years 5492-5563 (1732-1803), copied and sent to Dubnow by Ya'akov Shapiro of Mezrich, 8 pp., Hebrew
  - Mezrich (Miedzyrzec)[III.16], 1893 (Folder 949, Item 73970-73989)
    b) letter from Ya'akov Shapiro about the apostate Meyer (Paul) the Informer, 15 Sivan 5653, Hebrew, 5 pp.
  - Mezrich (Miedzyrzec)[III.16], undated (Folder 949, Item 73970-73989)
    c) the story of the City of Vahun, near Mezrich, a folk-tale recorded and annotated by Ya'akov Shapiro in Mezrich, Hebrew, 4 pp.
    other letters from Shapiro and A. Bialostotsky about this matter
  - Chronicles of Israel in the City of Mohilev Podolsk[III.17], undated (Folder 950, Item 73990-73991)
    inscriptions from old gravestones in the Mohilev cemetery from the years 5483-5552 (1723-1792), with annotations added by Menahem Litinsky